ALEX MACHIN-MAYES

GIS PROFESSIONAL

CONTACT

- **** 360-527-6216
- alexmachinmayes@gmail.com
- alexmachinmayes.github.io
- 618 W Connecticut St Bellingham, WA 98225

EDUCATION

MS, CARTOGRAPHY AND GIS

University of Wisconsin - Madison, 2021 Phi Kappa Phi | 4.0/4.0 GPA

BA, HUMAN GEOGRAPHY MINOR, GIS

Western Washington University, 2012

CORE SKILLS

- Geospatial Data Analysis
- Cartographic Visualization
- Spatial Databases
- GPS Data Collection
- Web Map Development

PROFICIENCIES

ESRI PRODUCTS

ArcGIS Desktop, ArcGIS Pro, ArcGIS Online, Collector, ArcPy, Model Builder, Web AppBuilder, ArcGIS Developer, Network Analyst, Spatial Analyst, COGO

GEODATABASES

ArcGIS Catalog, parcel fabrics, schemas, SQL expressions, topologies, coded value domains, LGIM, joins, relationships

RELATED TOOLS

QGIS, GPS data collection trainer, Adobe Creative Suite, Mapbox Studio, Trimble Pathfinder Office, Excel, U.S. Census data, research, writing, editing

WORKING KNOWLEDGE

ArcGIS API for JavaScript, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Bootstrap, Python, SQL, Leaflet, GitHub, GRASS, CAD

PROFILE

Self-driven and resourceful GIS expert with seven years of professional experience and an aptitude for learning and applying new tools. Brings advanced technical and analytical proficiencies, a geographic perspective, and a highly adaptable skill set. Seeking a role making meaningful contributions in a collaborative environment while continuing to learn and develop new skills.

EXPERIENCE

GIS CONSULTANT

Falcon Cultural Resources | Skagit County, WA (Remote) 2

2019-Present

- Produce archaeological site maps and shapefiles for reports to the DAHP.
- Provide GPS data processing and support for data collection in the field.
- Conduct viewshed analysis to visualize prominence of proposed development
- Utilize aerial, LiDAR, USGS topographic basemaps and web services to give historical and ecological context to site areas.

GIS PROPERTY SPECIALIST

Swinomish Indian Tribal Community | La Conner, WA

2014-2017

- Responsible for providing maps, analysis, database maintenance and support to a wide range of government departments, specialists, and technicians.
- Managed and maintained GIS data within the Planning Department system and published data for interdepartmental use to ArcGIS Online.
- Contributed to building and maintaining complex databases of government assets and features, including: zoning, parcels, buildings, roads, utilities, and natural and cultural resources.
- Produced maps and property updates through research and interpretation of land surveys, as-builts, legal property descriptions, and assessor records.
- Worked with environmental science specialists to survey and map wetland soil conductivity and assess the suitability of crops and restoration efforts.
- Collaborated with project managers to design and configure custom database schemas and ArcGIS Collector apps, enhancing GPS data collection efficiency.
- Led trainings on GPS data collection utilizing ArcGIS Collector for mobile devices, Trimble GPS receivers, and ArcGIS Online for data management.

GIS CONSULTANT

Independent Contractor | Bellingham, WA (Remote)

2012-2014

- Created a large forest roads database for salmon habitat restoration initiative using Road Maintenance and Abandonment Plan documents, georeferencing maps, and analysis of LiDAR and NAIP aerial imagery for digitization.
- Digitized the Nooksack River active channel footprint at large scale for an update to the National Hydrography Dataset.
- Assisted in the development of a comprehensive geodatabase and study template for studying steelhead habitat health indicators for the NWIFC.